<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Converted from multivariable_calculus/chapters/ch01-points-vectors-space.tex, Section 3.
     Status: CONVERTED. -->
<section xml:id="sec-1-coordinates-and-dimension" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Coordinates and dimension</title>

  <p>
    The last section ended with a quiet warning. A vector can be drawn as an arrow, but its
    coordinates depend on the directions and units we choose. Coordinates are not the vector
    itself; they are the vector written in a particular language.
  </p>

  <p>
    That language is still powerful. It lets us describe locations, directions, lines, planes,
    and higher-dimensional data with the same simple algebra.
  </p>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-spaces-r2-r3-rn">
    <title>The spaces <m>\mathbb R^2</m>, <m>\mathbb R^3</m>, and <m>\mathbb R^n</m></title>

    <p>
      A small warehouse robot moves along three natural directions: east-west, north-south,
      and up-down. If it starts at the charging station and moves to
      <md>(7,3,2),</md>
      we may read this as
      <md>7 \text{ meters east}, \qquad 3 \text{ meters north}, \qquad 2 \text{ meters up}.</md>
      The same list of numbers could describe a point, if we are locating the robot, or a
      vector, if we are describing a displacement.
    </p>

    <p>
      Two coordinates give the plane:
      <md>\mathbb R^2=\{(x,y):x,y\in\mathbb R\}.</md>
      Three coordinates give ordinary space:
      <md>\mathbb R^3=\{(x,y,z):x,y,z\in\mathbb R\}.</md>
      There is no reason to stop at three coordinates. A weather station might record
      <md>(\text{temperature},\text{pressure},\text{humidity},\text{wind speed}),</md>
      which is a point in a four-dimensional data space. We cannot draw four perpendicular axes
      on a page, but the algebra still works.
    </p>

    <definition xml:id="def-coordinate-space-rn">
      <title>The coordinate space <m>\mathbb R^n</m></title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          For a positive integer <m>n</m>, the space <m>\mathbb R^n</m> is the set of all
          ordered lists of <m>n</m> real numbers:
          <md>\mathbb R^n=\{(x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n):x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n\in\mathbb R\}.</md>
          The numbers <m>x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n</m> are called the <term>coordinates</term> of the
          point, or the <term>components</term> of the vector.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      The notation is the same for points and vectors because the same ordered lists are used
      for both. The meaning comes from the sentence around the notation.
    </p>

    <p>
      For example,
      <md>P=(7,3,2)</md>
      may mean a location in the warehouse. But
      <md>\mathbf v=(7,3,2)</md>
      may mean a displacement: move <m>7</m> east, <m>3</m> north, and <m>2</m> up.
    </p>

    <p>
      This is why we often use letters like <m>P,Q,A,B</m> for points and bold letters like
      <m>\mathbf u,\mathbf v,\mathbf w</m> for vectors. The notation helps us remember the
      difference, even though the coordinates look alike.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-standard-basis-vectors">
    <title>Standard basis vectors</title>

    <p>
      On a map, the coordinate pair <m>(3,2)</m> can be built from two basic moves:
      <md>3(1,0)+2(0,1)=(3,0)+(0,2)=(3,2).</md>
      The vector <m>(1,0)</m> means one unit in the first coordinate direction. The vector
      <m>(0,1)</m> means one unit in the second coordinate direction.
    </p>

    <p>
      These two vectors are so common that they get special names:
      <md>\mathbf e_1=(1,0), \qquad \mathbf e_2=(0,1).</md>
      In space we use
      <md>\mathbf e_1=(1,0,0), \qquad \mathbf e_2=(0,1,0), \qquad \mathbf e_3=(0,0,1).</md>
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="fig-standard-basis">
      <caption>The standard basis vectors build the usual coordinates in the plane.</caption>
      <image width="55%">
        <latex-image>
        \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.9, &gt;=stealth]
          \draw[-&gt;] (-0.4,0) -- (4.2,0) node[right] {\(x\)};
          \draw[-&gt;] (0,-0.4) -- (0,3.2) node[above] {\(y\)};
          \draw[step=1, gray!20, very thin] (0,0) grid (4,3);
          \draw[-&gt;, thick] (0,0) -- (1,0) node[midway, below] {\(\mathbf e_1\)};
          \draw[-&gt;, thick] (0,0) -- (0,1) node[midway, left] {\(\mathbf e_2\)};
          \draw[-&gt;, very thick] (0,0) -- (3,2) node[midway, above left] {\(3\mathbf e_1+2\mathbf e_2\)};
          \draw[dashed] (3,0) -- (3,2);
          \draw[dashed] (0,2) -- (3,2);
          \fill (3,2) circle (2pt);
          \node[above right] at (3,2) {\((3,2)\)};
          \node[below left] at (0,0) {\(0\)};
        \end{tikzpicture}
        </latex-image>
      </image>
    </figure>

    <definition xml:id="def-standard-basis-vectors">
      <title>Standard basis vectors</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          In <m>\mathbb R^n</m>, the standard basis vector <m>\mathbf e_j</m> is the vector
          whose <m>j</m>-th component is <m>1</m> and whose other components are <m>0</m>:
          <md>\mathbf e_j=(0,\ldots,0,1,0,\ldots,0).</md>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      Every vector in <m>\mathbb R^n</m> is built from the standard basis vectors:
      <md>(x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n)=x_1\mathbf e_1+x_2\mathbf e_2+\cdots+x_n\mathbf e_n.</md>
      This formula is more than notation. It says that coordinates are instructions:
      <md>x_1 \text{ steps in direction } \mathbf e_1,\quad x_2 \text{ steps in direction } \mathbf e_2,\quad \ldots</md>
      The standard coordinate system is the grid made from these standard directions.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="ex-displacement-in-space">
      <title>A displacement in space</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          A drone displacement is
          <md>\mathbf v=(4,-1,3).</md>
          Using the standard basis in <m>\mathbb R^3</m>,
          <md>\mathbf v=4\mathbf e_1-\mathbf e_2+3\mathbf e_3.</md>
          So the command says: move <m>4</m> units in the first direction, <m>-1</m> unit in
          the second direction, and <m>3</m> units in the third direction.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-coordinate-descriptions">
    <title>Coordinate descriptions of geometric objects</title>

    <p>
      Coordinates let us describe entire geometric objects, not only single points.
    </p>

    <p>
      A walking path in the plane starts at
      <md>P=(2,1)</md>
      and follows the direction
      <md>\mathbf u=(3,2).</md>
      The affine line from the previous section is
      <md>P+t\mathbf u=(2,1)+t(3,2).</md>
      Writing out the coordinates gives
      <md>x=2+3t,\qquad y=1+2t.</md>
      This is a <term>parametric</term> description of the line. The parameter <m>t</m> is a
      clock for the motion along the line.
    </p>

    <p>
      We can also remove <m>t</m>. From
      <md>x=2+3t</md>
      we get
      <md>t=\frac{x-2}{3}.</md>
      Substituting into <m>y=1+2t</m>,
      <md>y=1+\frac{2(x-2)}{3}.</md>
      After simplifying,
      <md>2x-3y=1.</md>
      So the same line has two descriptions:
      <md>\boxed{(x,y)=(2,1)+t(3,2)}</md>
      and
      <md>\boxed{2x-3y=1.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The parametric description tells us how to move along the line. The equation tells us how
      to test whether a point lies on the line.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="ex-plane-from-two-directions">
      <title>A plane from two directions</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          A tilted sheet of metal passes through the point
          <md>P=(1,0,2)</md>
          and contains the two directions
          <md>\mathbf u=(1,2,0), \qquad \mathbf v=(0,1,1).</md>
          Points on the sheet have the form
          <md>P+s\mathbf u+t\mathbf v.</md>
          Writing out the coordinates,
          <md>(x,y,z)=(1,0,2)+s(1,2,0)+t(0,1,1),</md>
          so
          <md>x=1+s,\qquad y=2s+t,\qquad z=2+t.</md>
          From the first and third equations,
          <md>s=x-1,\qquad t=z-2.</md>
          Substitute these into the equation for <m>y</m>:
          <md>y=2(x-1)+(z-2)=2x+z-4.</md>
          Thus the same plane can be written as
          <md>\boxed{(x,y,z)=(1,0,2)+s(1,2,0)+t(0,1,1)}</md>
          or as
          <md>\boxed{2x-y+z=4.}</md>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p>
      Equations and inequalities describe regions too. For example,
      <md>0\leq x\leq 12,\qquad 0\leq y\leq 8,\qquad 0\leq z\leq 3</md>
      describes a rectangular room that is <m>12</m> units long, <m>8</m> units wide, and
      <m>3</m> units high.
    </p>

    <p>
      The set
      <md>z=2</md>
      is a horizontal plane. The set
      <md>x=5</md>
      is a vertical plane. The set
      <md>x^2+y^2=1</md>
      in <m>\mathbb R^3</m> is a cylinder of radius <m>1</m> around the <m>z</m>-axis. The
      equation does not mention <m>z</m>, so <m>z</m> is free to take any value.
    </p>

    <p>
      This is a useful habit: when an equation does not mention one coordinate, the object
      extends freely in that coordinate direction.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-picture-stops-rn-still-works">
    <title>When a picture stops being possible: why <m>\mathbb R^n</m> still works</title>

    <p>
      The plane is easy to draw. Space is harder, but still visible. Four-dimensional space is
      different. There is no honest picture of four perpendicular coordinate axes in our
      ordinary three-dimensional world.
    </p>

    <p>
      But many useful objects are naturally four-dimensional or higher.
    </p>

    <p>
      A sensor in a greenhouse might record
      <md>(T,p,h,c),</md>
      where
      <md>T=\text{temperature},\quad p=\text{pressure},\quad h=\text{humidity},\quad c=\text{carbon dioxide level}.</md>
      This point lives in <m>\mathbb R^4</m>. A small change in the sensor reading might be
      <md>\Delta \mathbf s=(2,-0.1,5,0.03).</md>
      That means temperature rose by <m>2</m>, pressure fell by <m>0.1</m>, humidity rose by
      <m>5</m>, and carbon dioxide level rose by <m>0.03</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      We cannot draw this vector as an ordinary arrow. Still, we can add it, scale it, and
      compare it component by component:
      <md>(T,p,h,c)+\Delta \mathbf s=(T+2,\;p-0.1,\;h+5,\;c+0.03).</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      That is why <m>\mathbb R^n</m> is not just a strange abstraction. It is the natural home
      for any situation described by <m>n</m> numbers.
    </p>

    <p>
      The standard basis in <m>\mathbb R^4</m> is
      <md>
        <mrow>\mathbf e_1 \amp=(1,0,0,0),</mrow>
        <mrow>\mathbf e_2 \amp=(0,1,0,0),</mrow>
        <mrow>\mathbf e_3 \amp=(0,0,1,0),</mrow>
        <mrow>\mathbf e_4 \amp=(0,0,0,1).</mrow>
      </md>
      So
      <md>(T,p,h,c)=T\mathbf e_1+p\mathbf e_2+h\mathbf e_3+c\mathbf e_4.</md>
      The picture disappears, but the coordinate story remains.
    </p>

    <p>
      The standard basis works so smoothly that it hides the next question. What if we do not
      choose the standard directions? A city may have diagonal streets. A crystal may have
      slanted axes. A surface may carry its own natural grid. Some chosen directions work
      perfectly as coordinates; others are redundant or incomplete. The test for this is one of
      the most important ideas in the book: <term>linear independence</term>.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
