<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Converted from multivariable_calculus/chapters/ch01-points-vectors-space.tex, Section 1.
     Status: CONVERTED (proof-of-concept / reference template). -->
<section xml:id="sec-1-why-multivariable-calculus-begins-with-geometry" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Why multivariable calculus begins with geometry</title>

  <p>
    Single-variable calculus lived on a line. A point was described by one number, and
    there were only two directions to move: left or right. But many real-life questions do
    not live on a real line. A storm moves across a map, a satellite moves through space,
    and the temperature in a room depends on where you stand.
  </p>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-from-one-input-to-many">
    <title>From one input to many inputs</title>

    <p>
      Imagine a small weather station on the coast. A radar image says that the center of a
      storm cell is
      <md>12 \text{ km east}, \qquad 5 \text{ km north}</md>
      of the station. The location is naturally written as the ordered pair
      <md>P=(12,5).</md>
      A helicopter hovering above the same point needs a third number. If it is <m>0.8</m> km
      above the ground, its position is
      <md>H=(12,5,0.8).</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The numbers in these lists do not all have the same meaning. The first two numbers
      locate a point on a flat map. The third number locates height. But the idea is the
      same: a position is described by several coordinates.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="fig-storm-grid">
      <caption>The storm moves from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m>, requiring a larger coordinate grid.</caption>
      <image width="60%">
        <latex-image>
        \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.5, &gt;=stealth]
          % axes
          \draw[-&gt;] (-0.3,0) -- (18,0) node[right] {east};
          \draw[-&gt;] (0,-0.3) -- (0,11) node[above] {north};
          % grid
          \draw[step=1, gray!20, very thin] (0,0) grid (17,10);
          % Point P
          \fill (12,5) circle (3pt);
          \node[below right] at (12,5) {\(P=(12,5)\)};
          \draw[dashed] (12,0) -- (12,5);
          \draw[dashed] (0,5) -- (12,5);
          \node[below] at (12,0) {\(12\)};
          \node[left] at (0,5) {\(5\)};
          % Point Q
          \fill (15,9) circle (3pt);
          \node[above right] at (15,9) {\(Q=(15,9)\)};
          \draw[dashed] (15,0) -- (15,9);
          \draw[dashed] (0,9) -- (15,9);
          \node[below] at (15,0) {\(15\)};
          \node[left] at (0,9) {\(9\)};
          % displacement vector
          \draw[-&gt;, thick, blue] (12,5) -- (15,9) node[midway, above left] {\((3,4)\)};
          \fill (0,0) circle (2pt);
          \node[below left] at (0,0) {station};
        \end{tikzpicture}
        </latex-image>
      </image>
    </figure>

    <p>
      This is the first reason multivariable calculus begins with geometry. Before we can
      differentiate or integrate, we need to know where things are.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-position-displacement">
    <title>Position, displacement, and measured quantities</title>

    <p>
      Now suppose the storm moves. One hour later its center is
      <md>Q=(15,9).</md>
      We can subtract the coordinates to find the displacement:
      <md>Q-P=(15-12,\;9-5)=(3,4).</md>
      That means the storm moved <m>3</m> km east and <m>4</m> km north.
    </p>

    <p>
      If it moved in a straight line, the distance traveled is found from the same
      Pythagorean theorem used in the plane:
      <md>\sqrt{3^2+4^2}=5 \text{ km}.</md>
    </p>

    <example xml:id="ex-storm-displacement">
      <title>A storm displacement</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          The point
          <md>P=(12,5)</md>
          is a location. The ordered pair
          <md>(3,4)</md>
          is a displacement. It tells us how to move from <m>P</m> to <m>Q</m>:
          <md>(12,5)+(3,4)=(15,9).</md>
          The same displacement could start somewhere else:
          <md>(2,1)+(3,4)=(5,5).</md>
          So a displacement is not tied to one fixed place. It can be applied to any point.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p>
      This distinction is small, but it will save us from confusion later.
    </p>

    <p>
      A <term>point</term> is a location. A <term>vector</term> is a displacement.
      Coordinates let us write both with ordered lists, but the meanings are different.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-first-story">
    <title>A first story: locating a storm, a satellite, and a temperature reading</title>

    <p>
      The same coordinates can also be used as inputs to a function.
    </p>

    <p>
      At the point <m>(12,5)</m>, a weather sensor might report a temperature of
      <m>18^\circ</m>C. Then temperature is not itself a point. It is a number assigned to a
      point:
      <md>T(12,5)=18.</md>
      If the temperature is measured over a whole region, we have a function
      <md>T(x,y).</md>
      The input is a point on a map, and the output is a number.
    </p>

    <p>
      A satellite position is different. At time <m>t</m>, the satellite has three coordinates:
      <md>\mathbf r(t)=(x(t),y(t),z(t)).</md>
      Here the input is one number, time, but the output is a point in space.
    </p>

    <p>
      So several kinds of functions will appear in this book:
    </p>

    <table xml:id="tab-kinds-of-functions">
      <title>Kinds of functions appearing in this book.</title>
      <tabular>
        <row header="yes" bottom="medium">
          <cell>Situation</cell>
          <cell>Input</cell>
          <cell>Output</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>temperature on a map</cell>
          <cell><m>(x,y)</m></cell>
          <cell><m>T(x,y)</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>height of a hill</cell>
          <cell><m>(x,y)</m></cell>
          <cell><m>z=f(x,y)</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>satellite motion</cell>
          <cell><m>t</m></cell>
          <cell><m>\mathbf r(t)=(x(t),y(t),z(t))</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>wind in the plane</cell>
          <cell><m>(x,y)</m></cell>
          <cell><m>\mathbf F(x,y)</m></cell>
        </row>
      </tabular>
    </table>

    <p>
      The last example is especially important. A wind field assigns an arrow to every
      point. At one point the wind may blow east; at another, northeast; at another, not at
      all. Later, this idea will become a <term>vector field</term>. Vector fields are the
      natural language of fluids, force, electricity, magnetism, and many of the integral
      theorems near the end of the book.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-what-changes">
    <title>What changes from single-variable calculus, and what stays the same</title>

    <p>
      Single-variable calculus asked questions like these:
      <md>\text{How fast is } f(x) \text{ changing?}</md>
      and
      <md>\text{How much has accumulated from } a \text{ to } b?</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      Those questions remain. But the geometry changes.
    </p>

    <p>
      For a function of one variable, the graph is a curve in the plane. At a point, there is
      one main direction to move along the input line. For a function of two variables, the
      graph is usually a surface in space. At a point in the input plane, there are infinitely
      many directions to move.
    </p>

    <p>
      A hiker standing on a hillside can walk north, south, east, west, or along any slanted
      path between them. A single slope number no longer tells the whole story.
    </p>

    <p>
      The old ideas will return in new forms:
    </p>

    <table xml:id="tab-old-ideas-new-forms">
      <title>How single-variable ideas reappear in several variables.</title>
      <tabular>
        <row header="yes" bottom="medium">
          <cell>Single-variable calculus</cell>
          <cell>Multivariable calculus</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>number line</cell>
          <cell>plane and space</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>slope of a curve</cell>
          <cell>rates of change in many directions</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>tangent line</cell>
          <cell>tangent planes and tangent spaces</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>area under a graph</cell>
          <cell>area, volume, flux, and circulation</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>\int_a^b f'(x)\,dx=f(b)-f(a)</m></cell>
          <cell>boundary integrals equal interior integrals</cell>
        </row>
      </tabular>
    </table>

    <p>
      The last line is the long story of the book. The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus will
      not disappear. It will grow.
    </p>

    <p>
      For now, the next step is much simpler. The difference between two locations behaves
      like a reusable instruction:
      <md>\text{move } 3 \text{ east and } 4 \text{ north}.</md>
      That instruction is the first object we need to understand carefully. It is called a
      <term>vector</term>.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
