<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Converted from multivariable_calculus/chapters/ch18-generalized-stokes.tex, Section 18.7.
     Status: CONVERTED. -->
<section xml:id="sec-18-proof-ideas" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Proof ideas</title>

  <p>
    The generalized Stokes theorem now has four familiar faces:
    <md>\text{FTC},\qquad \text{Green},\qquad \text{classical Stokes},\qquad \text{divergence theorem}.</md>
    The proof idea is the same in all of them. First prove the theorem on a simple coordinate
    piece. Then cut a complicated object into many simple pieces. Interior boundary
    contributions cancel. The outside boundary remains.
  </p>

  <p>We start with the cleanest two-dimensional calculation.</p>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-proof-on-a-rectangle">
    <title>Proof on a rectangle</title>

    <p>
      Let
      <md>R=[a,b]\times[c,d]</md>
      with the standard orientation
      <md>dx\wedge dy.</md>
      Then <m>\partial R</m> is oriented counterclockwise.
    </p>

    <p>
      Take a <m>C^1</m> <m>1</m>-form
      <md>\omega=P(x,y)\,dx+Q(x,y)\,dy.</md>
      We will prove
      <md>\int_{\partial R}\omega=\int_R d\omega</md>
      directly.
    </p>

    <p>The boundary has four sides.</p>

    <p>
      On the bottom side <m>y=c</m>, <m>x</m> goes from <m>a</m> to <m>b</m>, and <m>dy=0</m>.
      The contribution is
      <md>\int_a^b P(x,c)\,dx.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      On the right side <m>x=b</m>, <m>y</m> goes from <m>c</m> to <m>d</m>, and <m>dx=0</m>.
      The contribution is
      <md>\int_c^d Q(b,y)\,dy.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      On the top side <m>y=d</m>, <m>x</m> goes from <m>b</m> back to <m>a</m>, and <m>dy=0</m>.
      The contribution is
      <md>-\int_a^b P(x,d)\,dx.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      On the left side <m>x=a</m>, <m>y</m> goes from <m>d</m> back to <m>c</m>, and <m>dx=0</m>.
      The contribution is
      <md>-\int_c^d Q(a,y)\,dy.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      Add them:
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_{\partial R}\omega \amp= \int_a^b P(x,c)\,dx + \int_c^d Q(b,y)\,dy</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\qquad - \int_a^b P(x,d)\,dx - \int_c^d Q(a,y)\,dy</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp= \int_c^d\bigl(Q(b,y)-Q(a,y)\bigr)\,dy - \int_a^b\bigl(P(x,d)-P(x,c)\bigr)\,dx.</mrow>
      </md>
    </p>

    <p>
      Now the single-variable Fundamental Theorem of Calculus enters twice:
      <md>Q(b,y)-Q(a,y)=\int_a^b Q_x(x,y)\,dx,</md>
      and
      <md>P(x,d)-P(x,c)=\int_c^d P_y(x,y)\,dy.</md>
      Therefore
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_{\partial R}\omega \amp= \int_c^d\int_a^b Q_x(x,y)\,dx\,dy - \int_a^b\int_c^d P_y(x,y)\,dy\,dx</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp= \iint_R (Q_x-P_y)\,dx\wedge dy.</mrow>
      </md>
      But
      <md>d\omega=(Q_x-P_y)\,dx\wedge dy.</md>
      So
      <md>\boxed{\int_{\partial R}\omega=\int_R d\omega.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      This proof is Green's theorem on a rectangle. It is also Stokes' theorem on a flat
      coordinate patch. The only tool inside it was the one-dimensional Fundamental Theorem of
      Calculus.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-proof-on-a-box">
    <title>Proof on a box</title>

    <p>The three-dimensional box calculation is the same idea with one more pair of faces.</p>

    <p>
      Let
      <md>B=[a,b]\times[c,d]\times[e,f]</md>
      with the standard orientation
      <md>dx\wedge dy\wedge dz.</md>
      Let
      <md>\Phi=P\,dy\wedge dz+Q\,dz\wedge dx+R\,dx\wedge dy.</md>
      Then
      <md>d\Phi=(P_x+Q_y+R_z)\,dx\wedge dy\wedge dz.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The <m>x</m>-faces contribute
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_{\text{\(x\)-faces}}\Phi \amp= \int_c^d\int_e^f \bigl(P(b,y,z)-P(a,y,z)\bigr)\,dz\,dy</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp= \int_c^d\int_e^f\int_a^b P_x(x,y,z)\,dx\,dz\,dy.</mrow>
      </md>
      The last equality is the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus in the <m>x</m>-direction.
    </p>

    <p>
      Similarly, the <m>y</m>-faces contribute
      <md>\int_B Q_y\,dx\,dy\,dz,</md>
      and the <m>z</m>-faces contribute
      <md>\int_B R_z\,dx\,dy\,dz.</md>
      Adding the three pairs of opposite faces gives
      <md>\boxed{\int_{\partial B}\Phi = \int_B (P_x+Q_y+R_z)\,dx\wedge dy\wedge dz = \int_B d\Phi.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      So the divergence theorem on a rectangular box is also just the Fundamental Theorem of
      Calculus, used once in each coordinate direction.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-interior-faces-cancel">
    <title>Interior faces cancel</title>

    <p>
      Now cut a larger rectangle into smaller rectangles. Apply the rectangle proof to each
      small rectangle:
      <md>\int_{\partial R_{ij}}\omega=\int_{R_{ij}}d\omega.</md>
      Then add the equations.
    </p>

    <p>
      On the right side, the small integrals combine:
      <md>\sum_{i,j}\int_{R_{ij}}d\omega=\int_R d\omega.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      On the left side, every interior edge is counted twice. One neighboring rectangle walks
      that shared edge in one direction. The other neighboring rectangle walks it in the
      opposite direction. A <m>1</m>-form integral changes sign when direction reverses, so the
      two contributions cancel.
    </p>

    <p>
      Only the outer boundary remains:
      <md>\sum_{i,j}\int_{\partial R_{ij}}\omega = \int_{\partial R}\omega.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The same cancellation happens in three dimensions. If a solid is cut into small boxes,
      then every interior face belongs to two neighboring boxes. One box gives the face one
      orientation; the other gives the opposite orientation. A <m>2</m>-form integral changes
      sign when the surface orientation reverses, so the two face integrals cancel.
    </p>

    <p>This is the geometric reason that only the outside boundary appears in Stokes' theorem.</p>

    <p>
      <md>\boxed{\text{interior boundaries cancel; exterior boundaries survive.}}</md>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-pullback-to-parameter-domains">
    <title>Pullback to parameter domains</title>

    <p>
      The rectangle and box proofs live in coordinate space. A curved surface or a curved solid
      is usually handled by parametrizing it.
    </p>

    <p>
      For a surface, suppose
      <md>\mathbf r:D\subseteq\mathbb R^2\to S\subseteq\mathbb R^3</md>
      is a smooth oriented parametrization. A <m>1</m>-form <m>\omega</m> in space pulls back to
      a <m>1</m>-form on the parameter region:
      <md>\mathbf r^*\omega.</md>
      Surface integrals also pull back:
      <md>\int_S d\omega=\int_D \mathbf r^*(d\omega).</md>
      Boundary integrals pull back as well:
      <md>\int_{\partial S}\omega=\int_{\partial D}\mathbf r^*\omega.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The link between the two sides is the identity
      <md>\boxed{\mathbf r^*(d\omega)=d(\mathbf r^*\omega).}</md>
      This is the chain rule written in the language of forms.
    </p>

    <p>
      Now apply Green's theorem on the parameter region <m>D</m>:
      <md>\int_{\partial D}\mathbf r^*\omega = \int_D d(\mathbf r^*\omega).</md>
      Using the pullback identity,
      <md>\int_D d(\mathbf r^*\omega) = \int_D \mathbf r^*(d\omega).</md>
      Translating back to the surface gives
      <md>\boxed{\int_{\partial S}\omega=\int_S d\omega.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>This is classical Stokes' theorem on a parametrized surface.</p>

    <p>
      For a solid coordinate map
      <md>T:C\subseteq\mathbb R^3\to E\subseteq\mathbb R^3,</md>
      the same pattern gives
      <md>T^*(d\Phi)=d(T^*\Phi).</md>
      So Stokes on the coordinate box <m>C</m> becomes Stokes on the curved solid <m>E</m>, with
      the Jacobian and orientation signs carried automatically by the pullback.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-approximation-by-small-pieces">
    <title>Approximation by small pieces</title>

    <p>
      A general region is not one rectangle. A general surface is not one parameter patch. A
      general solid is not one box.
    </p>

    <p>
      But many of the objects in this book can be cut into finitely many simple pieces, or
      approximated by many small simple pieces:
      <md>\text{rectangles in the plane}, \qquad \text{parameter patches on a surface}, \qquad \text{boxes in space}.</md>
      On each piece, the theorem is a coordinate calculation. When the pieces are added, the
      interior boundaries cancel.
    </p>

    <p>
      For a curved boundary, there is a small extra step. A grid of rectangles does not fit the
      boundary perfectly. Some small pieces near the edge are cut off. As the grid becomes
      finer, the leftover boundary error shrinks. The <m>C^1</m> condition on the form and the
      piecewise smooth condition on the boundary make that shrinking error controllable.
    </p>

    <p>
      That is why the theorem allows corners but not wild boundaries. A polygon is fine. A box
      is fine. A smooth surface made from finitely many patches is fine. A boundary so jagged
      that it has no tangent direction in any ordinary sense is outside the rules of this
      course.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-what-is-hidden-in-a-fully-rigorous-proof">
    <title>What is hidden in a fully rigorous proof</title>

    <p>
      The proof idea is simple enough to see:
      <md>\text{prove on simple pieces, then cancel interior boundaries.}</md>
      A fully rigorous proof has to check several details.
    </p>

    <p>
      First, the object must be covered by pieces whose parameter maps are well behaved. For
      surfaces, this means smooth regular patches. For solids, this means pieces that can be
      handled by coordinate maps or by limits of boxes.
    </p>

    <p>
      Second, overlaps must be counted with the right signs. If two pieces share an interior
      edge or face, their induced orientations must be opposite. This is exactly what the
      boundary orientation rules in <xref ref="sec-18-boundaries-and-orientation"/> were
      designed to guarantee.
    </p>

    <p>
      Third, the integrals over small leftover pieces must go to zero as the pieces shrink. This
      is where compactness, piecewise smoothness, and <m>C^1</m> coefficients enter the proof.
      They keep the quantities being integrated from behaving wildly while the mesh gets
      smaller.
    </p>

    <p>
      Fourth, the form must be defined on an open set containing the whole object. A singularity
      inside the region cannot be ignored. The punctured-plane form
      <md>\frac{-y}{x^2+y^2}\,dx+\frac{x}{x^2+y^2}\,dy</md>
      and the inverse-square flux form
      <md>\frac{x}{r^3}\,dy\wedge dz + \frac{y}{r^3}\,dz\wedge dx + \frac{z}{r^3}\,dx\wedge dy</md>
      showed exactly what goes wrong. A missing point can be detected by a loop or a closed
      surface around it.
    </p>

    <p>
      These details are not new ideas. They are the careful bookkeeping needed to make the
      cancellation proof honest.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s7-subsec-two-twin-facts">
    <title>Two twin facts: <m>\partial^2=0</m> and <m>d^2=0</m></title>

    <p>
      <xref ref="ch17-exterior-derivatives"/> proved the algebraic fact
      <md>\boxed{d^2=0.}</md>
      This chapter keeps using the geometric fact
      <md>\boxed{\partial(\partial M)=\emptyset.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>They are twins.</p>

    <p>
      If Stokes' theorem is applied twice, it says
      <md>\int_M d(d\omega) = \int_{\partial M}d\omega = \int_{\partial(\partial M)}\omega.</md>
      The left side is zero because
      <md>d^2\omega=0.</md>
      The right side is zero because a boundary has no boundary.
    </p>

    <p>
      So the two slogans match:
      <md>\boxed{\text{the derivative of a derivative is zero}}</md>
      and
      <md>\boxed{\text{the boundary of a boundary is empty.}}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      This is more than a coincidence. The operator <m>d</m> is the algebraic mirror of the
      boundary operator <m>\partial</m>. Stokes' theorem is the bridge between them:
      <md>\int_{\partial M}\omega=\int_M d\omega.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The theorem has now been stated, used, and partly explained. What remains is to strip away
      the old names and place the four disguises side by side. The next section is the
      translation table: intervals, plane regions, surfaces, and solids all saying the same
      sentence in their own dialect.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
