<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Converted from multivariable_calculus/chapters/ch18-generalized-stokes.tex, Section 18.9.
     Status: CONVERTED. -->
<section xml:id="sec-18-warning-examples" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Warning examples</title>

  <p>
    The grand table in <xref ref="sec-18-the-grand-translation-table"/> compresses many theorems into one
    line:
    <md>\int_{\partial M}\omega=\int_M d\omega.</md>
    But the line is not a spell. It is a precise sentence. Each hypothesis tells us how to read
    the sentence correctly.
  </p>

  <p>This section collects the most common ways the formula is misread.</p>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s9-subsec-boundary-orientation-reversed">
    <title>Boundary orientation reversed</title>

    <p>
      Start with the simplest two-dimensional example:
      <md>R=[0,1]\times[0,1],</md>
      oriented by
      <md>dx\wedge dy.</md>
      The induced boundary orientation is counterclockwise.
    </p>

    <p>
      Take
      <md>\omega=x\,dy.</md>
      Then
      <md>d\omega=dx\wedge dy.</md>
      So the interior integral is
      <md>\int_R d\omega=\int_R dx\wedge dy=1.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      Now compute the boundary integral with the correct orientation. The bottom edge and top
      edge have
      <md>dy=0,</md>
      so they contribute <m>0</m>. On the right edge,
      <md>x=1,\qquad 0\le y\le1,</md>
      so
      <md>\int_{\text{right edge}}x\,dy=\int_0^1dy=1.</md>
      On the left edge,
      <md>x=0,</md>
      so the contribution is <m>0</m>. Therefore
      <md>\boxed{\int_{\partial R}\omega=1=\int_Rd\omega.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      But if we walk the same square clockwise, every line integral changes sign:
      <md>\int_{-\partial R}\omega=-1.</md>
      The interior integral is still
      <md>\int_R d\omega=1.</md>
      So the false statement would be
      <md>-1=1.</md>
    </p>

    <p>The theorem did not fail. We used the wrong boundary orientation.</p>

    <md>\boxed{\text{The boundary orientation is not optional.}}</md>

    <p>
      The same warning appears for surfaces. If a disk is oriented upward, its boundary is
      counterclockwise when viewed from above. If we keep the upward surface but walk the
      boundary clockwise, Stokes' theorem changes sign on only one side. The two sides no longer
      match.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="c18s9-fig-boundary-orientation-reversed">
      <caption>Reversing the boundary direction reverses the boundary integral.</caption>
      <image width="70%">
        <latex-image>
        \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.9, &gt;=stealth]
            \begin{scope}
                \draw[fill=gray!10, thick] (0,0) rectangle (2.4,2.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, red!65!black] (0,0) -- (1.2,0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, red!65!black] (2.4,0) -- (2.4,1.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, red!65!black] (2.4,2.0) -- (1.2,2.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, red!65!black] (0,2.0) -- (0,1.0);
                \node at (1.2,-0.6) {correct};
                \node at (1.2,-1.05) {region on the left};
            \end{scope}

            \begin{scope}[shift={(5.0,0)}]
                \draw[fill=gray!10, thick] (0,0) rectangle (2.4,2.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, blue!65!black] (0,0) -- (0,1.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, blue!65!black] (0,2.0) -- (1.2,2.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, blue!65!black] (2.4,2.0) -- (2.4,1.0);
                \draw[-&gt;, very thick, blue!65!black] (2.4,0) -- (1.2,0);
                \node at (1.2,-0.6) {reversed};
                \node at (1.2,-1.05) {sign changes};
            \end{scope}
        \end{tikzpicture}
        </latex-image>
      </image>
    </figure>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s9-subsec-missing-boundary-components">
    <title>Missing boundary components around holes</title>

    <p>A hole is not empty bookkeeping. It creates an inner boundary.</p>

    <p>
      Let
      <md>A=\{(x,y):1\le x^2+y^2\le4\}</md>
      be the annulus between the circles of radius <m>1</m> and <m>2</m>. Use the standard
      orientation
      <md>dx\wedge dy.</md>
      The outer boundary is counterclockwise, and the inner boundary is clockwise.
    </p>

    <p>
      Take the area-measuring form
      <md>\omega=\frac12(-y\,dx+x\,dy).</md>
      Then
      <md>d\omega=dx\wedge dy.</md>
      So
      <md>\int_A d\omega=\operatorname{Area}(A)=4\pi-\pi=3\pi.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      Now compute the boundary integral. On a counterclockwise circle of radius <m>r</m>,
      <md>x=r\cos t,\qquad y=r\sin t,\qquad 0\le t\le2\pi.</md>
      Then
      <md>dx=-r\sin t\,dt,\qquad dy=r\cos t\,dt.</md>
      Substitute:
      <md>
        <mrow>\omega \amp= \frac12\left(-r\sin t(-r\sin t\,dt)+r\cos t(r\cos t\,dt)\right)</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp= \frac12r^2\,dt.</mrow>
      </md>
      So a counterclockwise circle of radius <m>r</m> contributes
      <md>\pi r^2.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The outer circle contributes
      <md>4\pi.</md>
      The inner circle has radius <m>1</m>, but it is oriented clockwise, so it contributes
      <md>-\pi.</md>
      Therefore
      <md>\boxed{\int_{\partial A}\omega=4\pi-\pi=3\pi.}</md>
      This matches
      <md>\int_A d\omega=3\pi.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      If we forgot the inner boundary, we would get
      <md>4\pi,</md>
      which is wrong.
    </p>

    <md>\boxed{\text{The boundary of a region with holes has all its boundary components.}}</md>

    <p>
      The same warning holds in three dimensions. A solid shell
      <md>b\le x^2+y^2+z^2\le a^2</md>
      has two boundary spheres. The outer sphere is oriented outward from the shell, away from
      the origin. The inner sphere is also oriented outward from the shell, which points toward
      the origin. That sign is exactly what makes flux contributions cancel when the field has no
      source inside the shell.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s9-subsec-singularities-inside-region">
    <title>Singularities inside the region</title>

    <p>
      Some forms look harmless on the boundary but fail inside. Stokes' theorem needs the form to
      be defined on an open set containing the whole object <m>M</m>, not only on
      <m>\partial M</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Consider the <m>1</m>-form
      <md>\alpha=\frac{-y}{x^2+y^2}\,dx+\frac{x}{x^2+y^2}\,dy.</md>
      It is defined on
      <md>\mathbb R^2\setminus\{(0,0)\}.</md>
      Where it is defined,
      <md>d\alpha=0.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      On the unit circle
      <md>C:\quad x=\cos t,\qquad y=\sin t,\qquad 0\le t\le2\pi,</md>
      we have
      <md>dx=-\sin t\,dt,\qquad dy=\cos t\,dt.</md>
      So
      <md>
        <mrow>\alpha \amp= (-\sin t)(-\sin t\,dt)+(\cos t)(\cos t\,dt)</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp= dt.</mrow>
      </md>
      Therefore
      <md>\boxed{\int_C\alpha=2\pi.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      A careless argument would say:
      <md>d\alpha=0,\qquad \text{so } \int_C\alpha=0.</md>
      But that argument tries to use Stokes' theorem on the unit disk. The form <m>\alpha</m> is
      not defined at the origin, and the origin lies inside the disk. The theorem is not
      available.
    </p>

    <p>
      If we remove a small disk around the origin, the theorem works again. The region is an
      annulus:
      <md>\varepsilon\le x^2+y^2\le1.</md>
      On that annulus,
      <md>d\alpha=0.</md>
      The outer boundary contributes
      <md>2\pi.</md>
      The inner boundary is clockwise, so it contributes
      <md>-2\pi.</md>
      The total boundary integral is
      <md>2\pi-2\pi=0,</md>
      matching
      <md>\int_{\text{annulus}}d\alpha=0.</md>
    </p>

    <p>The singularity did not disappear. We turned it into a boundary component.</p>

    <md>\boxed{\text{A missing point inside can be detected by a loop around it.}}</md>

    <p>
      There is a three-dimensional version of the same warning. Let
      <md>r=\sqrt{x^2+y^2+z^2}</md>
      and consider the flux <m>2</m>-form
      <md>\Psi=\frac{x}{r^3}\,dy\wedge dz+\frac{y}{r^3}\,dz\wedge dx+\frac{z}{r^3}\,dx\wedge dy.</md>
      This is the flux form of
      <md>\mathbf G=\frac{(x,y,z)}{r^3}.</md>
      The field is not defined at the origin. Away from the origin,
      <md>d\Psi=0.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      Yet the outward flux through a sphere of radius <m>a</m> is
      <md>4\pi.</md>
      It would be wrong to apply the divergence theorem to the whole ball and conclude zero flux.
      The form is not defined at the origin. If we remove a smaller ball around the origin, the
      outer flux <m>4\pi</m> and inner flux <m>-4\pi</m> cancel, just as they should.
    </p>

    <p>
      A singularity inside a region behaves like a source the ordinary derivative does not see,
      because the ordinary derivative is not defined there.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s9-subsec-smoothness-assumptions">
    <title>Smoothness assumptions and piecewise smooth objects</title>

    <p>
      The theorem also asks for the form to be smooth enough. In this book, the safe condition
      is:
      <md>\omega\text{ has }C^1\text{ coefficients}</md>
      on an open set containing <m>M</m>.
    </p>

    <p>A jump can hide an internal boundary.</p>

    <p>
      Let
      <md>R=[-1,1]\times[-1,1],</md>
      and define
      <md>H(y)=\begin{cases}0, &amp; y&lt;0,\\1, &amp; y\ge 0.\end{cases}</md>
      Consider the <m>1</m>-form
      <md>\omega=H(y)\,dx.</md>
      This form is not continuous across the line
      <md>y=0.</md>
      It is certainly not <m>C^1</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      If we ignore the jump and look only on the two open halves of the square, then <m>H</m> is
      constant on each half, so a careless computation would say
      <md>d\omega=0.</md>
      That would suggest
      <md>\int_{\partial R}\omega=0.</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      But compute the boundary integral directly. On the bottom edge, <m>y=-1</m>, so
      <md>H(y)=0,</md>
      and the contribution is <m>0</m>. On the right and left edges,
      <md>dx=0,</md>
      so the contribution is <m>0</m>. On the top edge, <m>y=1</m>, and the positive boundary
      orientation travels from
      <md>x=1\quad\text{to}\quad x=-1.</md>
      There
      <md>H(y)=1,</md>
      so the top contributes
      <md>\int_1^{-1}dx=-2.</md>
      Thus
      <md>\boxed{\int_{\partial R}\omega=-2.}</md>
    </p>

    <p>
      The jump along <m>y=0</m> is hiding an internal edge. The <m>C^1</m> theorem is not
      designed to ignore that edge. More advanced versions of Stokes' theorem can handle jumps,
      but then the jump contributes its own term.
    </p>

    <p>Smoothness of the boundary is a separate issue.</p>

    <p>
      A rectangle is allowed even though it has corners. Its boundary is made of finitely many
      smooth edges. A box is allowed even though it has edges and corners. Its boundary is made
      of finitely many smooth faces. That is what piecewise smooth means.
    </p>

    <p>Corners do not create extra terms. Interior shared edges cancel.</p>

    <p>
      For example, split the rectangle
      <md>[0,2]\times[0,1]</md>
      into two rectangles:
      <md>R_1=[0,1]\times[0,1],\qquad R_2=[1,2]\times[0,1].</md>
      The shared edge is
      <md>x=1,\qquad 0\le y\le1.</md>
      As part of <m>\partial R_1</m>, that edge is traveled upward. As part of
      <m>\partial R_2</m>, the same edge is traveled downward. The two line integrals cancel for
      every <m>1</m>-form:
      <md>\int_{\text{shared edge from }R_1}\omega+\int_{\text{shared edge from }R_2}\omega=0.</md>
      Only the outside boundary survives.
    </p>

    <p>So the warning is not <q>corners are bad.</q> The warning is more precise:</p>

    <md>\boxed{\begin{array}{c}
\text{finite piecewise smooth geometry is allowed,}\\[1mm]
\text{but jumps, singularities, and wild boundaries are not covered by the basic theorem.}
\end{array}}</md>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c18s9-subsec-the-checklist">
    <title>The checklist</title>

    <p>
      Before using
      <md>\int_{\partial M}\omega=\int_M d\omega,</md>
      check the grammar.
    </p>

    <md>\begin{array}{c|l}
\text{Check} \amp \text{Question} \\ \hline
\text{Degree} \amp
\omega\text{ has degree }\dim M-1\text{?}\\[1mm]
\text{Boundary} \amp
\text{Is every boundary component included?}\\[1mm]
\text{Orientation} \amp
\text{Does }\partial M\text{ have the induced orientation?}\\[1mm]
\text{Domain} \amp
\omega\text{ is defined on an open set containing }M\text{?}\\[1mm]
\text{Smoothness} \amp
\omega\text{ has }C^1\text{ coefficients where needed?}\\[1mm]
\text{Geometry} \amp
M\text{ and }\partial M\text{ are compact and piecewise smooth?}
\end{array}</md>

    <p>
      When one of these checks fails, the formula may still have a more advanced version. But the
      missing condition must be paid for. A reversed orientation pays with a minus sign. A
      missing hole pays with an extra boundary component. A singularity pays by acting like a
      hidden source. A jump pays by creating an internal edge or sheet.
    </p>

    <p>
      This is why the generalized Stokes theorem is both simple and strict. It gives one sentence
      for the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus, Green's theorem, Stokes' theorem, and the
      divergence theorem. But the sentence only works when every word is read correctly.
    </p>

    <p>
      The chapter review will turn this into practice: translate the old vector formulas into
      forms, choose the right boundary, and decide which side of the theorem is easier to
      compute. After that, the same boundary idea begins to move in time. A conserved quantity
      changes inside a region only because it flows through the boundary. That is where Stokes'
      theorem becomes the language of conservation laws.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
