<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Converted from multivariable_calculus/chapters/ch13-vector-fields-line-integrals.tex, Section 13.1.
     Status: CONVERTED. -->
<section xml:id="sec-13-vector-fields" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Vector fields</title>

  <p>
    A scalar field attaches one number to each point. A temperature field says,
    <q>at this point, the temperature is <m>21^\circ\text{C}</m>.</q> A height field
    says, <q>at this point, the height is <m>80</m> meters.</q>
  </p>

  <p>
    A vector field attaches an arrow to each point. A wind field says, <q>at this point,
    the air is moving northeast at this speed.</q> A force field says, <q>at this point, a
    particle would be pulled in this direction with this strength.</q>
  </p>

  <subsection xml:id="c13s1-subsec-vector-at-every-point">
    <title>A vector attached to every point</title>

    <p>
      Picture a shallow circular fountain. Water swirls around the center. Put the center
      at the origin, and suppose the horizontal velocity of the water at the point
      <m>(x,y)</m> is
      <md>\mathbf V(x,y)=\frac14(-y,x).</md>
      At a few points,
    </p>

    <table xml:id="c13s1-tab-fountain-values">
      <title>Sample values of the fountain field <m>\mathbf V(x,y)=\frac14(-y,x)</m>.</title>
      <tabular>
        <row header="yes" bottom="medium">
          <cell><m>(x,y)</m></cell>
          <cell><m>\mathbf V(x,y)</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell><m>(4,0)</m></cell><cell><m>(0,1)</m></cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>(0,4)</m></cell><cell><m>(-1,0)</m></cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>(-4,0)</m></cell><cell><m>(0,-1)</m></cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>(0,-4)</m></cell><cell><m>(1,0)</m></cell></row>
      </tabular>
    </table>

    <p>
      So water on the right side moves upward, water at the top moves left, water on the
      left moves downward, and water at the bottom moves right. The arrows circle around
      the origin.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="c13s1-fig-fountain-field">
      <caption>A vector field attaches an arrow to every point of its domain.</caption>
      <image width="70%">
        <latex-image>
        \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.62, &gt;=stealth]
            \draw[-&gt;] (-4.7,0) -- (4.9,0) node[right] {\(x\)};
            \draw[-&gt;] (0,-4.7) -- (0,4.9) node[above] {\(y\)};

            \draw[gray!20, step=1] (-4,-4) grid (4,4);

            \foreach \x in {-3,-2,-1,0,1,2,3} {
                \foreach \y in {-3,-2,-1,0,1,2,3} {
                    \draw[-&gt;, blue!65!black, thick]
                        (\x,\y) -- ++({-0.20*\y},{0.20*\x});
                }
            }

            \draw[thick] (0,0) circle (4);
            \node at (0,-5.25) {\(\mathbf V(x,y)=\frac14(-y,x)\)};
        \end{tikzpicture}
        </latex-image>
      </image>
    </figure>

    <p>
      This picture is not one moving particle. It is a whole instruction book. If a tiny
      floating leaf reaches the point <m>(2,3)</m>, the field tells the leaf what velocity
      to have there:
      <md>\mathbf V(2,3)=\frac14(-3,2)=\left(-\frac34,\frac12\right).</md>
    </p>

    <definition xml:id="c13s1-def-vector-field">
      <title>Vector field</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          A <term>vector field</term> on a region <m>D</m> in the plane is a function
          <md>\mathbf F:D\subseteq\mathbb R^2\to\mathbb R^2.</md>
          Usually we write
          <md>\mathbf F(x,y)=(P(x,y),Q(x,y)).</md>
        </p>
        <p>
          A vector field on a region <m>D</m> in space is a function
          <md>\mathbf F:D\subseteq\mathbb R^3\to\mathbb R^3,</md>
          usually written
          <md>\mathbf F(x,y,z)=(P(x,y,z),Q(x,y,z),R(x,y,z)).</md>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      The input is a point. The output is a vector. We draw the output vector with its
      tail placed at the input point.
    </p>

    <p>
      The domain matters. The formula
      <md>\mathbf F(x,y)=\frac{1}{x^2+y^2}(-y,x)</md>
      looks like a swirling field, but it is not defined at the origin. Its domain is
      <md>\mathbb R^2\setminus\{(0,0)\}.</md>
      That missing point will become important later, when we study conservative fields.
      A tiny hole can change the behavior of every closed curve around it.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c13s1-subsec-velocity-force-gradient">
    <title>Velocity fields, force fields, and gradient fields</title>

    <p>Vector fields appear in several different roles.</p>

    <p>
      A <term>velocity field</term> tells how a fluid or moving crowd flows. The fountain
      field
      <md>\mathbf V(x,y)=\frac14(-y,x)</md>
      is a velocity field. It assigns a velocity vector to every point in the water.
    </p>

    <p>
      A <term>force field</term> tells what force would act on a particle placed at each
      point. For example, a simplified gravitational field pointing toward the origin has
      the form
      <md>\mathbf G(x,y,z)=-\frac{k}{(x^2+y^2+z^2)^{3/2}}(x,y,z),</md>
      where <m>k\gt 0</m>. The vector <m>(x,y,z)</m> points away from the origin, so the
      negative sign points back toward the origin. The denominator says the field weakens
      with distance.
    </p>

    <p>
      A <term>gradient field</term> comes from a scalar field. If
      <md>f(x,y)</md>
      is a differentiable scalar field, then
      <md>\nabla f(x,y)=\bigl(f_x(x,y),f_y(x,y)\bigr)</md>
      is a vector field.
    </p>

    <p>
      For example, let
      <md>h(x,y)=100+4x+3y-x^2-y^2.</md>
      This could be a simple height model for a hill. Its gradient field is
      <md>\nabla h(x,y)=(4-2x,\;3-2y).</md>
      At the point <m>(1,1)</m>,
      <md>\nabla h(1,1)=(2,1).</md>
      A hiker standing there sees the steepest uphill direction pointing roughly east and
      slightly north.
    </p>

    <p>
      Recall from <xref ref="sec-9-the-gradient-and-level-sets"/> that gradients cross
      level curves at right angles. So a gradient field is not just a collection of arrows;
      it is tied to the contour map of the scalar field that produced it.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="c13s1-ex-not-gradient-field">
      <title>A field that is not a gradient field, at least not obviously</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          The swirling field
          <md>\mathbf V(x,y)=(-y,x)</md>
          has arrows tangent to circles centered at the origin. If it were the gradient of
          some height function, its arrows would be perpendicular to that height function's
          level curves. But these arrows go around in circles. They look more like rotation
          than uphill motion.
        </p>
        <p>
          Later we will learn a test that detects this difference. Some fields are gradients
          in disguise. Others carry genuine circulation.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c13s1-subsec-sketching-vector-fields">
    <title>Sketching vector fields</title>

    <p>
      A vector field drawing cannot show every arrow. There are infinitely many points. A
      sketch chooses representative points and draws enough arrows to reveal the pattern.
    </p>

    <p>Here are four basic fields in the plane.</p>

    <table xml:id="c13s1-tab-basic-fields">
      <title>Four basic vector fields in the plane.</title>
      <tabular>
        <row header="yes" bottom="medium">
          <cell>Field</cell>
          <cell>Formula</cell>
          <cell>Pattern</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell>constant field</cell><cell><m>(1,0)</m></cell><cell>all arrows point right</cell></row>
        <row><cell>radial source</cell><cell><m>(x,y)</m></cell><cell>arrows point away from the origin</cell></row>
        <row><cell>radial sink</cell><cell><m>(-x,-y)</m></cell><cell>arrows point toward the origin</cell></row>
        <row><cell>rotational field</cell><cell><m>(-y,x)</m></cell><cell>arrows circulate counterclockwise</cell></row>
      </tabular>
    </table>

    <p>
      The length of an arrow matters, but only up to the scale of the drawing. If one arrow
      is too long, it can hide the rest of the picture. It is common to shorten all arrows
      while preserving their directions, or to draw only direction arrows. A sketch is meant
      to show structure, not to be a measuring device.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="c13s1-ex-sketch-saddle-field">
      <title>Sketching a saddle-like field</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Consider
          <md>\mathbf F(x,y)=(x,-y).</md>
          On the <m>x</m>-axis, where <m>y=0</m>,
          <md>\mathbf F(x,0)=(x,0).</md>
          So arrows point away from the origin along the <m>x</m>-axis.
        </p>
        <p>
          On the <m>y</m>-axis, where <m>x=0</m>,
          <md>\mathbf F(0,y)=(0,-y).</md>
          So arrows point toward the origin along the <m>y</m>-axis.
        </p>
        <p>
          This field pushes outward in one direction and inward in the perpendicular
          direction. The origin is a saddle-type equilibrium: motion near it is attracted
          from some directions and repelled in others.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p>A few practical rules help when drawing a field.</p>

    <table xml:id="c13s1-tab-drawing-steps">
      <title>Practical steps for sketching a vector field.</title>
      <tabular>
        <row header="yes" bottom="medium">
          <cell>Step</cell>
          <cell>What to look for</cell>
        </row>
        <row><cell><m>1</m></cell><cell>Evaluate the field at simple points.</cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>2</m></cell><cell>Look along axes or symmetry lines.</cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>3</m></cell><cell>Find points where <m>\mathbf F=\mathbf 0</m>.</cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>4</m></cell><cell>Notice whether arrows point outward, inward, around, or across.</cell></row>
        <row><cell><m>5</m></cell><cell>Scale arrows so the pattern can be seen.</cell></row>
      </tabular>
    </table>

    <p>
      The points where
      <md>\mathbf F(\mathbf p)=\mathbf 0</md>
      are called <term>equilibrium points</term>. If the field is a velocity field, a
      particle placed exactly at such a point does not move.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="c13s1-subsec-flow-lines">
    <title>Flow lines and qualitative behavior</title>

    <p>
      A vector field tells a moving particle what velocity it should have at each point. A
      path that obeys the field is called a flow line.
    </p>

    <p>
      For the fountain field
      <md>\mathbf V(x,y)=(-y,x),</md>
      the circle
      <md>\mathbf r(t)=(R\cos t,R\sin t)</md>
      is a flow line. Its velocity is
      <md>\mathbf r'(t)=(-R\sin t,R\cos t).</md>
      But
      <md>\mathbf V(\mathbf r(t))=\mathbf V(R\cos t,R\sin t)=(-R\sin t,R\cos t).</md>
      So
      <md>\mathbf r'(t)=\mathbf V(\mathbf r(t)).</md>
      The particle follows the arrows exactly.
    </p>

    <definition xml:id="c13s1-def-flow-line">
      <title>Flow line</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Let <m>\mathbf F</m> be a vector field. A differentiable curve
          <md>\mathbf r(t)</md>
          is called a <term>flow line</term> of <m>\mathbf F</m> if
          <md>\boxed{\mathbf r'(t)=\mathbf F(\mathbf r(t))}</md>
          for every <m>t</m> in its interval of definition.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      The equation
      <md>\mathbf r'(t)=\mathbf F(\mathbf r(t))</md>
      says that the curve's velocity at each moment equals the arrow assigned by the field
      at the curve's current position.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="c13s1-ex-flow-lines-radial">
      <title>Flow lines of a radial field</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Let
          <md>\mathbf F(x,y)=(x,y).</md>
          If a particle starts at
          <md>\mathbf r(0)=(a,b),</md>
          then
          <md>\mathbf r(t)=(ae^t,be^t)</md>
          is a flow line, because
          <md>\mathbf r'(t)=(ae^t,be^t)=\mathbf r(t)=\mathbf F(\mathbf r(t)).</md>
          The particle moves along the ray through <m>(a,b)</m>, away from the origin. The
          origin is an equilibrium point, but nearby points are pushed outward.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <example xml:id="c13s1-ex-flow-lines-saddle">
      <title>Flow lines of a saddle field</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          For
          <md>\mathbf F(x,y)=(x,-y),</md>
          a flow line through <m>(a,b)</m> is
          <md>\mathbf r(t)=(ae^t,be^{-t}).</md>
          Then
          <md>\mathbf r'(t)=(ae^t,-be^{-t})=\mathbf F(ae^t,be^{-t}).</md>
          If <m>ab\ne0</m>, the product of the coordinates along the flow is
          <md>x(t)y(t)=ae^t\cdot be^{-t}=ab.</md>
          So the flow lines lie on hyperbolas
          <md>xy=\text{constant}.</md>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p>
      A vector field drawing is therefore a prediction device. It tells us where motion is
      fast or slow, where it turns, where it settles, and where it circulates.
    </p>

    <p>
      But motion is only one thing we can do with a curve. A curve can also carry material.
      A wire can have density. A trail can have snow depth. A cable can have temperature.
      Those quantities are not arrows, but they still need to be added along a path. Before
      we let vector fields do work, we need the simpler integral that adds scalar quantities
      along curves.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
